hello everyone this is Frank defrays
welcome to another week of Holo talk
for the week of October 4th I believe I
don't have my calendar here believe it
or not
I believe it's October 4th in any case
we have a new format this week uh Holo
talk is being broken up into individual
segments this gives you the listener an
option of coming under the hall talk
page and choosing specifically what it
is that you wish to listen to
three segments will be the welcome
message and news of the week which
you're listening to right now
the second segment each week we'll deal
with listeners emails and telephone
calls I won't answer their questions on
the air and the third segment will be
the main topic area and also the segment
that will have all the special guests
now you may come on to the show each
week and you may not be interested in
the listeners email questions or one of
the other segments and you just want to
hear the interview you now have that
ability to do so by just choosing
segment three if you'd like to listen to
the entire program there will also be a
separate link that will play the program
from its entirety from start to finish
without having to choose whatever it is
that you want to listen to so there's a
number of different options for you and
I hope without any feedback regarding
this change is welcome please send it to
me I'm interested in hearing whether you
think this is a good idea or a bad idea
whether you like it or you don't like it
so on and so forth
this week's topic is going to be the
holographic heart this was a special
presentation that was made on World News
Tonight last week by Peter Jennings and
it takes a look at a new device which
allows surgeons to work in virtual
reality with a human heart that
floats in space
and we're also going to take a look at
the definition of hologram and
holography what is a hologram and what
isn't a hologram it's something just
because it floats in space a hologram or
do we need to have a very specific
definition of what a hologram is or as a
third option do we need to widen or
broaden the scope of the definition of
the word holography to accommodate the
new technology so you'll find all of
that in segment three we also have our
first video presentation this week I
digitized the World News Tonight
presentation and you can take a look at
holographic heart as well you'll find
that link right after the third segment
our news for this week laser diagnostic
Technologies has been awarded a small
business Innovation research Grant from
the National Institutes of Health to
continue to evaluate an exciting new
scanning laser technology that measures
blood flow in the optic nerve and may
help find the cause of glaucoma and
other site-threatening diseases that
affect millions of Americans each year
the new instrument uses the same Doppler
Principle as that employed in radar guns
as a speeding car causes a shift in the
frequency of radar waves that can be
detected at its velocity or speed
measured the new instrument measures
shift in the frequency of light caused
by moving blood cells
laser diagnostic Technologies ink a
six-year-old venture-funded medical
device Company in San Diego specializes
in developing diagnostic process
products for the eye
coming in from Irvine California and a
move to further strengthen its position
as a leading provider of high Precision
manufacturing equipment for the
fast-growing fiber optic Communications
Marketplace Newport Corporation Tuesday
announced that it has signed a
definitive agreement to acquire
environmental optic sensors Inc of
Boulder Colorado in a cash transaction
additional terms were not disclosed
complete completion of the acquisition
is subject to certain terms and
conditions but is expected to occur
within the next 30 days
and this wire is from September 29th
environmental Optical sensors a
privately held company founded in 1991
is a manufacturer of tunable external
cavity diode laser systems
Newport Corporation is a global leader
in a design manufacturer and marketing
of high Precision components instruments
and Integrated Systems to the fiber
optic Communications semiconductor
equipment computer peripherals and
scientific research markets
the company's Innovative products are
designed to enhance productivity and
capabilities of test and measurement and
automated assembly for precision
manufacturing engineering and research
applications there are two news items
that came through this week
if you would like to continue on with
holotalk you can go to segment two where
we're going to be answering listeners
questions
and if you'd like to go right to the
holographic art that's in segment three
hello everyone welcome to the listeners
question email and telephone call
section of hollow talk we do not get any
telephone calls this week but we got a
few emails and I'd like to answer them
for you here on the air today
this email is from Paul and Paul says I
hope you don't mind this beginner's
question no Paul that's what we're all
about we're here to answer research and
find out the information that you need
and answer them right here on whole talk
no matter what the level is of your
interest in lasers or holography
Paul goes on to ask I was wondering if
the Laser Technology that is used to
create Holograms can be used on humans
without danger to digitize a person in
3D
I hope I understand what is meant by
this hollow stuff I'm assuming it's the
same technology that has been used for
example to digitize fragile artwork and
then people can view the art in 3D
Paul there's
this is the perfect question for this
show because we're actually dealing with
this issue in segment three with the
holographic heart but there's a lot of
different ways to create
three-dimensional images and information
and on television you'll notice you've
got 3D logos that spin around
but they're not Holograms
there's a lot of programs where such as
QuickTime virtual reality where you can
spin an art object in space on your
computer monitor and see it 360 Degrees
also top and bottom
but that is not holography
we're really at a point where we have to
take a look and see what is a hologram
and what isn't a hologram but
traditional methods of creating
Holograms are going into a lab having an
Optics table that contains lenses
mirrors beam Splitters plate holders and
Laser
and taking that laser and Illuminating
the object and either doing a single
beam or split beam but creating drew
that method interference fringes in the
recording media and with very high
resolution
for all practical purposes uh
photographic plate that's sensitive to
the wavelength of the laser light that
you're using upon developing that plate
or film and Shining a light on it at the
same angle that was used to create it
you see the object appear in front of
you again that's the traditional method
of creating a hologram using a laser to
scan someone and then digitize them and
put that information into a computer
would certainly give you a
three-dimensional rotatable view of that
person or object but whether it would be
considered a hologram or not it's pretty
much up in the air and I would have to
say for that particular technology no
that is not a that is not a hologram
Carolyn wrote in and said where can I
purchase equipment for holographs
website catalog ordering local retail on
South Central Ohio
I would recommend right on the whole
talk page you'll notice a link to Ross
books
to purchase equipment to start doing
your own hologram it would be worthwhile
to pick up a copy of What's called the
holography marketplace which lists all
of the Distributors all of the
manufacturers all of the places where
you can order your lasers your Optics
your table if you decide to purchase one
instead of build one everything that you
need and everything that you want to
know about the holography industry is in
that book now keep in mind you're going
to pay a lot of different money for the
same items for instance ordering a laser
through a regular science supply house
may run you quite a bit of money but
there are also companies which buy
lasers manufacturers over ones and
things of that nature which are able to
offer lasers to you at quite a bit a
discount and savings
you'll be able to find out about this in
the holography marketplace so I would
suggest you click on that link go over
there take a look at the holography
marketplace I don't it's not a very very
expensive investment and I guarantee you
that if you want to get involved with
Holograms
that you will definitely that book will
definitely pay for itself many times
over through the information that's in
there to get you started to do your own
Holograms so it's not like you're going
to be out the money
to save many times the cost of that book
through the information that it will
provide to you
Karen has a question
I have a question I was hoping you would
be able to help me out or know someone
who could
when you look at a hologram why can you
only see it if you've got a light sword
shining on it from a certain angle
if you could help me out I would greatly
appreciate it when you re-illuminate a
hologram after it's completed if it's a
white light hologram or even a laser
hologram that needs laser light to
illuminate it you must make sure that
you match the same incoming angle that
was used to create the Hologram for
instance you take your holographic plate
and you put it in the plate holder and
you have a specific angle that that
laser beam is coming into the plate
and you must make sure that when you
process the plate you mad at you frame
it you put it on your wall if it happens
to be a reflection hologram
that your light is coming in at the same
angle to view the hologram
next question is from Dean
he says I am a student who's very
interested in holography I'm extremely
extremely interested in projection of
freestanding Holograms you know like in
the science fiction movies I know there
is a way to produce them and I am sure
that some of them probably already is
however I have found little information
on the subject and I am dying to learn
more I would be very grateful to you if
you could point me in the right
direction
tell me where I could find information
on the subject on the web or in books
videos Etc or even tell me how I could
get in touch with someone who could help
me
and that's from Dean
Dean the reason why you're not finding a
lot of information on the web about this
is that most Holograms need a recording
media in order to work whether it would
be a holographic plate or a holographic
film now granted it is possible to shoot
a hologram where you have parts of the
object actually projecting out in space
toward the viewer
and if a hologram is set up properly you
may even be able to shoot Holograms
where you have an object itself which
seemingly floats in space in front of
that plate
but the idea of creating an object that
just hangs in space
is something that's just not possible to
do at this point
through holography the laws of physics
themselves state that anytime that
you're using light something has to be
there to stop it and to take a laser
beam and send it through the air and
somehow draw out whatever it is that
you're looking to see
three-dimensionally doesn't work very
well because there's nothing there to
stop the beam now in some of the laser
light shows and I believe this is where
some people get some of the
misinformation they'll use either some
steam
or what I've seen at several laser light
shows they'll use a fine mist of falling
water to pass that laser beam through
and this happens to when the laser beam
goes through to draw whatever image it
is it happens to light up that water or
that Steam
but it's not a completely
three-dimensional image even though you
see it rotating it's rotating because
the computer program is telling it to
appear to be turning
but if you have a wall of water or Steam
that's showing you this image there's
nothing in that image which is going to
be closer to you or further away from
you
like in a hologram it's all going to be
in the plane of the water
and the steam even though the computer
program is telling that object to rotate
it is making the calculations to make it
look
like it's rotating
and if you want to get some more
information
on free floating objects and possibly
three-dimensional free-floating objects
using other Technologies you may want to
go on to segment three for the
holographic heart go into the video
watch the video and there's also a link
for the web page which is a new
technology that was developed to show
freestanding images in space
and we also
in that segment are asking the question
is this a hologram or isn't it a
hologram so those are our questions for
the week folks if you have laser and
holography questions send them into
whole talk the email address is whole
talk at holyworld.com or you can call in
toll-free across the USA
1-800-458-3525 leave your question on
the voicemail I'll take the question off
of the voicemail and use your voice on
the show so thank you for tuning in to
this segment the next segment is segment
three which is the holographic heart I
hope you enjoy it this is Frankie
Freitas for listeners questions on
holotalk
hello everyone this is our third and
final segment from the new format that
we're using for hollow talk
is the main part of the program and
today we're going to be taking a look at
something new from a company in New York
City called dimensional media Associates
which is the holographic heart
along with this look that we're going to
take at this we're going to also try and
answer a question what is a hologram now
apparently this
new holographic heart uses a different
technology and a different technique
from traditional holography we do not
have holographers in the laboratory with
lasers
creating holograms on film or plates
so we're also going to take a look and
see what is a hologram what can we say
is a hologram and what should we say
isn't a hologram I don't know if we're
going to be able to answer that question
to tell you the truth because I've done
a lot of looking into different things
I'm going to share with you today such
as definitions and patents
and it still may be up in the air
in any case we also have our first video
with holotalk this week and it was
recorded with Peter Jennings on World
News Tonight and you'll find that link
directly below this one so you can watch
the video of holographic heart
Peter Jennings himself when he comes on
the air he says Holograms are
three-dimensional floating images
they are light projected into space
the definition that Peter Jennings gives
on the introduction to the holographic
quad however the person who's being
interviewed one of the representatives
that uses this technology and was
working on developing it never refers to
the heart as a hologram
which refers to it as an image or a
three-dimensional image let's take a
look at the plus release found at the
dimensional media Associates Inc website
which I also have a link to if you'd
like to go there yourself and see what
they have to say about this technology
the holographic heart and also the other
things they are working on
dimensional media Associates Inc VMA is
a New York City based technology company
that designs develops manufactures and
distributes unique floating image 3D
volumetric visualization systems
our clients are an advertising
entertainment science medicine and
education founded in 1994 as a
partnership and Incorporated in June
1996 dma has positioned itself as a
market leader in 3D display technology
at the heart of dma's business is a
patented breakthrough technology which
dma developed for producing true 3D
aerial images without using lasers and
without requiring viewers to wear
special eyeglasses or virtual reality
headsets or sit in the dark
full color full motion images appear to
floating space and can be seen from wide
viewing angles under ambient lighting
conditions
3D visualization is the presentation of
images in ways that bring out the
three-dimensional nature of their
content drawings paintings and
photographs that show perspectives are
example of 3D visualization as are
images showing perspective in movies and
on television
images produced by 3D computer Graphics
are also examples
these are all representations of
three-dimensional objects but are
themselves actually only two-dimensional
creation of the illusion that an image
is itself three-dimensional can be
accomplished with viewing appliances
such as the stereoscopes of previous
generations or the special goggles used
to view 3D movies or the headsets used
in the creation of virtual reality
environments
in general those devices present
slightly different images to the left
and right eyes of viewers to achieve the
simulation of depth
recently however a breakthrough
technology was created by dimensional
media Associates Inc that actually
produces true three-dimensional images
without using lasers and without
requiring viewers to wear special
appliances further the full color full
motion images can be seen from wide
viewing angles in sizes up to 10 feet
and under ambient lighting conditions
called high definition volumetric
display hdvd for short
the technology makes use of input from a
variety of image generation and storage
sources real-time process data real
objects television computer monitors and
flat panel displays the projected images
appear to float in space and are so real
that view feel that they can reach out
and interact with them
hdvd uses a complex array of Precision
Optical components such as parabolic
mirrors and beam Splitters to collect
focus and then project light into space
to form real volumetric images
with this remarkable technology dma
provides multi-purpose volumetric 3D
visualization systems for use for
example in science medicine education
entertainment and advertising
as an example of this work dma under
contract from DARPA
delivered a 3D real-time virtual reality
surgical simulation system targeted for
training military surgical units not
only will the system provide 3D floating
images of human organs it will also
provide tactile and visual feedback to
Physicians and students as they interact
with the images doing the surgical
simulations
with these r d efforts dma aims to
create a new generation of visual
technology
now we have to ask how wide a definition
do we want to have for the word hologram
or holography which is the process of
creating Holograms
can we say that any any image that is
floating in space
is a hologram
now I know myself
as many of you probably know who have
worked with holography
and as many listeners who have never
worked with photography at all may know
just from thinking
we get a lot of questions asking about
floating images Holograms and usually
we try our best in the most polite way
possible to explain that just because an
image is floating in space does not
necessarily make it a hologram more than
likely not a hologram and it's another
technology that's used to create it
but do we have to re-examine this
and broaden our scope of a hologram or
holography
I went to Graham saxby's book practical
holography and I found the following
somewhat definitions of this
we found that the term hologram was
coined in 1948
by Dennis Gabor with the prefix
Hollow coming from a Greek word meaning
whole and the syllable gram from another
Greek word
conventionally signifying a drawing or
other visual representation
the term holography was coined by g.l
Rogers and I've tried to find some
information on GL Rogers on the on the
net and I had not turned up anything so
I will continue to look into that
it also because I want to say the
holograph is a document that is in the
author's handwriting although the Oxford
English Dictionary does accept holograph
as an alternative to hologram
to the physicist a hologram is a record
of the interference of two beams of
coherent light
which are mutually co-related in the
form of a microscopic pattern of
interference fringes
to the informed layperson it is a
photographic film or played which has
been exposed to laser light and
processed in such a way that one
illuminated
properly
it produces a three-dimensional image
less well-informed people often seem to
think of a hologram simply as some sort
of three-dimensional photograph
now to summarize this
we go on to read a hologram is a
complete record of the information and
when
correctly illuminated it will generate a
replica of the object wavefront enabling
the viewer to see an image which in
every respect replicates the object with
full parallax
I think one of the most important things
through all this to keep in mind is this
a hologram is a record of the
interference of two beams of coherent
light which are mutually co-related in
the form of a microscopic pattern of
interference fringes this is a very
specific definition and can only be done
coherent light or laser light
now I want to also to look at some of
the patents and I pulled some of them
uh let's see the one that I want to
refer to here
actually I pulled three of them patent
three three five zero six three two
seven from 1970 that was Emmett Leaf
that's the uh Patel patent
3838-903 from 74 and 3838 904 from 74 as
well but I'd like to focus on the first
which was three 506 327 from 1970.
this patent excuse me
is um
titled wavefront reconstruction using a
coherent reference beam
the word hologram itself was used right
in the first paragraph first sentence in
the abstract of disclosure if you've
ever had a chance to see patents there's
a very short single paragraph
description of what the patent is all
about so the word hologram itself was
used in this patent in the first
paragraph first sentence of the abstract
of disclosure and it goes on to say
the method of an apparatus for
constructing and reconstructing
Holograms of the off-axis type wherein
coherent radiation is directed onto an
object to provide an object-bearing beam
in the path of which is positioned a
detector sensitive to the coherent
radiation and I would assume that
although the word detector
I believe was probably put in there to
cover advances in technology at the time
detector probably was referring to film
or plates light sent to the film or
plates
and
the factor of advancement was built into
that word as we go into more electronic
holography
now here's the line that's important
this invention relates to methods and
apparatus for producing interference
Fringe patterns I.E
Holograms
and reconstructing the interference
Fringe pattern to produce one or more
images
so folks
we need to decide what it is that
we need to do about this definition of
holography apparently from some of the
patents and from some of the books that
deal specifically with holography in
order for something to be considered a
hologram
it must be created with coherent light
producing interference Fringe patterns
that is a hologram if whatever it is
that you're looking at
was not created with coherent light
used to produce interference patterns
and then those interference patterns
going on to recreate the object
then it must not be a hologram
but do we need to look at it and think
that we've got new technologies that are
doing just about the same thing such as
quote the holographic heart
should it be called a hologram
well like I said when we started up this
segment we probably would not get any
concrete answers to what is or what is
not a hologram
and I will throw the ball into your
court let you take a look at the video
clip
and sit back and think for a while what
is and what is not a hologram do we need
to broaden this definition to include
different ways of producing
three-dimensional images floating in
space and continue to call them
Holograms
or
do we say that
the Hologram has to have coherent light
producing interference fringes
and those interference fringes
reconstructing the actual image
okay folks the next step for you to do
is to move on to the segment four which
is the video itself watch it and I'm
going to close out the show if you have
any questions on lasers and Holograms
feel free to send them in and we come
back every week with a new show we've
got lots of guests coming up so I hope
you continue to tune back into whole
talk this is Frankie Freitas thank you
very much for tuning in and I'll see you
next week